[MUSIC]
[음악]
Okay, so that's one way to retrieve a document of interest.
관심 문서 검색하는 방법 하나를 알아봤습니다
Just take all articles out there, scan over them, and
모든 기사를 훑어보고
find the one that's most similar according to the metric that we define.
우리가 정의한 기준에서 가장 유사한 기사를 찾습니다
But another thing we might be interested in doing is clustering documents that
다른 방법은 관련 문서를
are related, so for example.
클러스터링하는 것인데 예를 들어
You might have a whole bunch of articles about sports or world news or
스포츠, 국제 뉴스 등의 기사가 있을 때
different things like this, and if we can structure our corpus in this way,
이렇게 말뭉치를 구조화해두면
if a person is reading an article that's about sports,
스포츠 기사를 읽고 있을 때
then we can very quickly search over all the other articles about sports,
전체 말뭉치의 모든 기사를 살펴보기보다
instead of looking at every article that's out there in the entire corpus.
재빨리 다른 스포츠 기사만을 검색할 수 있습니다
But the challenge here is the fact that these articles aren't going to have
하지만 어려운 점은 이 기사들에 라벨이
labels.
없다는 것입니다
It's not gonna be like the New York Times, where you go and
뉴욕 타임즈처럼 접속하면
somebody says, this is an education article.
교육 기사라고 알려주는 게 아니죠
Okay, and all we have are articles, and what we like to do, or
기사가 있을 때
discover these underlying groups of articles.
잠재된 기사 그룹을 발견하고자 합니다
Okay, so the goal is to discover these groups or clusters of related articles,
목표는 이런 관련 기사 그룹, 클러스터를 발견하는 것인데
and like I mentioned, one might represent a set of articles like sports, and
말씀드린 것처럼 스포츠, 세계 뉴스 등을
another one a set of articles about world news.
기사 집합으로 표현하는 것이죠
For the time being, let's actually assume that someone provides us with labels,
지금은 그냥 라벨이 주어진다고 가정합니다
so, somebody goes through and reads every article or
누군가 말뭉치의 모든 기사,
at least a large sub-set of articles in our corpus and labels them and
적어도 대부분의 기사를 읽고 라벨을 붙였는데
says, okay, these articles, these are all about sports.
이쪽 기사의 주제가 스포츠라고 합니다
And these ones, these are about world news.
그리고 이쪽은 세계 뉴스고요
And these about entertainment.
이쪽은 연예입니다
And these ones are about science.
이쪽은 과학이고요
So we have some set of articles that have labels associated with them.
라벨이 붙은 기사 모음이 있는 것이죠
Well, in this case, when we have our query article and we like to
검색 기사가 있고 라벨을 붙여서
sign it to a cluster, this ends up being just a multi-class classification problem.
클러스터로 묶으면 다중 클래스 분류 문제가 됩니다
Because the question is just, here is my query article,
검색 기사가 있고
I don't know the label associated with it, and I have a bunch of label document.
해당 라벨이 뭔지 모르는 상태에서 라벨 붙은 문서가 여럿 있으니 말이죠
I have the labels world news, science, sports, entertainment, technology,
세계 뉴스, 과학, 스포츠, 연예, 기술 등의 라벨이 있는데
and I just wanna classify which class this article belongs to, okay?
그중 기사가 어디 속하는지 분류하려는 거죠 맞나요?
So this is the question.
이게 문제입니다
It's just a multi class classification problem.
그렇다면 다중 클래스 분류 문제로 환원되죠
So if that were the case, that would be an example of a supervise learning problem.
여기에 해당한다면 지도 학습 문제가 되겠죠
[MUSIC]
[음악]